# Joan Gamell, Engineering Manager

gamell [at] gamell [dot] io

+1 (415) 825 2758

http://gamell.io

http://github.com/gamell

http://www.linkedin.com/in/gamell

Technologist bred and fascinated by the web. Broad experience in **full stack development**, made the jump to **management** but still coding when there is the chance. Thrive in the **mix of technical and leadership roles**, looking at management from the problem solving perspective and striving to improve every day. Kept my tech skills up to date by "scratching my own itch" with some open-source projects.

## Professional Experience

## Engineering Manager at Expedia in San Francisco, Jul 2015 - present

Expedia is one of the world's largest Online Travel Agent (OTA)

Having hands-on technical skills in this managerial position helped me to scale and lead an energetic team of engineers who owned the whole stack and deployed to production daily following Continuous Deployment practices.

- Built and led a successful team of Developers and Technical Project Manager who owned the complete Product & Tech Stack and reliably delivered according to Product's expectations.
- **Doubled team's size** by on-boarding new team members in two new remote locations in less than two months while minimizing the impact on sprint velocity and deliverables.
- Overcame the **challenges of leading a distributed team across 4 locations in 3 distant timezones** and adjusted the team's processes for optimal performance in this remote configuration.
- Hired new team members in a competitive market satisfying the given timeframe.
- **Mentored and coached team members**, empowering them to take decisions and to continuously improve themselves through data and feedback, and worked through performance issues with team members when needed.
- Laid out the technical vision for the product, liaise and collaborate with other teams.
- Ensured quality is built-in and automated in the code and pipeline.
- Wrote code, pair coding, perform code reviews and help debug issues. Main languages used are JavaScript, Java, HTML and

Tech Lead / Technical Project Manager at Expedia in San Francisco, Oct 2014 - Jul 2015

First role with people manager responsibilities in a small team of engineers where we owned the whole product.

- Led the effort to scale the system to serve x5 more requests with the same team.
- Performed as main project point person and liaison with other teams and Product stakeholders.
- Assumed the de-facto role of a **Technical Project Manager** / Delivery Manager and perfected the team's semi-kanban process.
- Hired, on-boarded and mentored new team members.
- Headed **front-end development** in the team, using mainly vanilla JS, LESS/CSS, HTML and node.
- Estimated new feature effort levels and worked with Product on Backlog planning/grooming.

Front-end Engineer at Expedia in Singapore, Oct 2012 - Oct 2014

Main front-end developer of a fully-responsive, high-traffic, highly-available e-commerce website: AirAsiaGo (https://www.airasiago.com). Used Kanban & Continuous Deployment methodologies and followed Clean Code practices.

- **Developed, tested and shipped** cross-browser, responsive, retina-ready features and modules built with HTML5, JavaScript jQuery, Backbone, AngularJS etc CSS3 (LESS), SVG, sprites, etc. on top of a Spring (Java) back-end.
- Led the team's front-end vision and development. Evangelize best practices by mentoring team mates.
- Interacted with UI Design team, providing constant feedback on the difficulty/feasibility of the planned features.
- **Optimized** page load-time and SEO ranking through minification, caching, selective loading, changes in front-end architecture, usage of subdomain-per-asset CDNs, sprite and image compression, etc.
- Identified, debugged and fixed live-site issues within hours (Splunk, Nagios, AWS monitoring, Google Analytics, etc.).

### Sr. Web Developer & Tech Lead at Optimum Solutions (Standard Chartered Bank) in Singapore, Jan - Oct 2012

Optimum Solutions is a Singaporean mid-size IT consultant company. SCB is a global bank with branches in 70 countries over 80,000 employees

Worked on the RMWB (Relation Manager WorkBench) project for Standard Chartered Bank. Our responsibility was to develop and ship the front-end of the application the corporate customers would use.

- Integrated an already existing web application from a third-party vendor following given designs and using HTML, CSS, JavaScript and JSPs into the RMWB portal which also grouped information from CreditMate and MicroStrategy Systems in a web-based interface. Developed web services to expose data from the backend with Spring (Java).
- Conducted technical interviews for Web Developer and Web Designer roles.
- Drove implementation, Quality Control, bug tracking and feature planning for the project.
- Undertook the role of **point of contact** between the Business and tech team.

#### Analyst at BBVA in Madrid, Sep 2010 - Dec 2011

BBVA is the second-largest Spanish bank with more than 100,00 employees around the world

Worked on the Mentor project at Wholesale Banking & Asset Management, Global Risk Unit. Mentor was a web-based project to integrate, unify, organize and report all the unit's risk data from diverse systems with different data outputs.

- Helped design and code the project's foundations from scratch (Maven config files, project file structure, initial setup).
- **Developed a complex parser** for a legacy system output (Algorithmics) making exhaustive use of Regular Expressions to translate the output to comprehensive, coherent JPA models.
- **Designed and implemented a web-based user-facing interface** with JSP, HTML and JavaScript (jQuery, Ajax, async plugin loading).
- Spearheaded **front-end development** and ensured best practices were followed.
- Drove meetings with Business stakeholders to gather requirements and design new features.

#### Developer at Safelayer Secure Communications in Barcelona, Feb 2009 - Sep 2010

Safelayer is an IT security company with ~50 workers

**Invented, designed and implemented** a proof of concept of gOTP, a novel two-factor authentication system which combined the robustness of One Time Passwords and the easily-remembered Graphical Passwords. The project was initially developed as a joint R&D Final Degree Project at UPC (see below) and Safelayer company, to become a product of the latter.

- Developed iPhone application as the client. Developed with <code>Objective-C</code>, <code>Cocoa Touch Framework</code>, <code>Xcode</code>.
- Built Grails (Groovy on Rails) application as the server. Used Groovy, Java, ant, Maven, SVN, MySQL, ExtJS (Sencha), Web Services.

## Education

Informatics Engineering, 2004-2009 at Barcelona School of Informatics (FIB), Technical University of Catalonia (UPC), Barcelona (Spain)

Degree + MSc Graduated with Honors in the final Degree project "A Secure Authentication System via OTP and Graphical Password (http://goo.gl/tkahus)"

## Other courses

- Startup Engineering, 2013 at Coursera (Stanford University)
- Spring Training, 2011 at SpringSource University
- iPhone Application Programming, 2009 at iTunesU (Stanford University)

## Additional Information

- Languages: Native Spanish and Catalan speaker. Full Professional Proficiency in English.
- My two passions are:
  - **Photography**: Have won prizes, had pictures featured in several editorials (e.g. 500px editors choice) and contributed thousands of dollars to charity by auctioning my pictures. **My portfolio (http://500px.com/gamell)**
  - Traveling: Have traveled to more than 35 countries and continuously thinking where to go next.